Colleen Wiessner Papers
Colleen Wiessner Papers
1998-2009
Wiessner, Colleen Aalsburg.
2 linear ft.
Papers of Dr. Colleen Wiessner, adult educator, relating to her work in the field of transformative learning, particularly in organizing conferences. Includes conference proceedings, research notes, photographs, audiocassettes, minicassettes, and computer media.
4795967
Biographical History
Dr. Colleen Aalsburg Wiessner (1954-2009) was an American scholar specializing in adult education. She was an assistant professor in the Department of Leadership, Policy, and Adult and Higher Education at North Carolina State University. Receiving her Master's and Doctorate from Teacher's College, Columbia University, she studied under Dr. Jack Mezirow, who originated the concept of transformative learning. While Mezirow's student, she helped to coordinate the First National Conference on Transformative Learning in 1998, and continued to be involved in the recurring conference until her death in 2009. Renamed the International Conference on Transformative Learning two years after its start, the conference still continues under the name of the International Transformative Learning Conference.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Colleen Wiessner Papers consists of audio recordings, computer media, documents related to Wiessner's conferences and professional work, Wiessner's writings, and miscellaneous photographs and other printed material.
Audio recordings consists of cassettes containing interviews with specific individuals such as Jack Mezirow, as well as on specific topics such as Work Place Learning and conferences.
Computer media contains items related to conferences, as well as notes, articles, and research, including work by and related to Jack Mezirow.
Conferences consists of documents related to Wiessner's work on the International Conference on Transformative Learning, including conference proceedings, participant feedback, and promotional material.
Professional work includes items related to Wiessner's research involving focus groups, completed feedback forms from the NCSU New Learning Project, and notes on education theory.
Writings contains papers written by Wiessner, including items written while a Master's student under Jack Mezirow.
Miscellaneous contains abstracts of education papers; photographs, including some from an unidentified conference; and printed material, primarily items advertising books and events related to transformative learning and social advocacy.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into six series, with each series arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
See also the
Jack Mezirow Papers
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Mezirow, Jack, 1923-2014.; Wiessner, Colleen Aalsburg.; International Transformative Learning Conference.; Adult education -- United States.; Transformative learning.; Transformative learning -- Congresses.; Education -- Philosophy.; Audiocassettes.; Brochures.; Conference proceedings.; Floppy disks.; Photographs.; Presentations (communicative events); Research notes.; Sound recordings.; Typescripts.
Access Restrictions
Access to recordings requires advance notice to create a use copy.
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Victoria Marsick, 2016.
Inventory
- Audio recordings, Media descriptions are transcribed verbatim from items' existing labels.
  - CIU COP, undated; wiessner_c_015; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)
  - Ed O’Sullivan, Parts 1 and 2, 04/22/2004; wiessner_c_010; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)
  - Elizabeth Kasl, Parts 1 and 2, 04/22/2004; wiessner_c_011; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)
  - Elizabeth Kasl, 04/22/2004; wiessner_c_012; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)
  - Jack Mezirow, Parts 1 and 2, 04/14/2004; wiessner_c_008; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)
  - Jack Mezirow, Parts 3 and 4, 04/14/2004; wiessner_c_009; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)
  - DC-SCH-1-1; John Dirkx, undated; wiessner_c_013; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)
  - JSW-ST-1-1; Jasper (No.2), undated; wiessner_c_001; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)
  - JSW-P-1-2, undated; wiessner_c_002; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)
  - JSW-P-2-1; Practitioner Interview, undated; wiessner_c_003; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)
  - Maxine Greene, 12/06/1997; wiessner_c_004; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)
  - [Victoria] Marsick, Work Place Learning, Part 1, 04/17/1998; wiessner_c_005; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)
  - [Victoria] Marsick, Work Place Learning, Part 2, 04/17/1998; wiessner_c_006; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)
  - Victoria Marsick, Reflections on the Conferences (1-5), 04/05/2004; wiessner_c_007; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)
  - [Unknown], undated; wiessner_c_014; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)
- Computer media, Media descriptions are transcribed verbatim from items' existing labels.
  - Advent Readings, undated; wiessner_c_018; Advent Readings: Orem King, (Winthrop); Euro-Amer. Collab.; Parhen; Lennard/ Thompson/ Booth; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - Boot (Emergency), undated; wiessner_c_044; Emergency boot disk; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - Carolyn Masterson Notes, undated; wiessner_c_031; Carolyn Masterson Notes, (done); Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - Conference Proceeding from [Nil.Pfahl?], undated; wiessner_c_029; Conference Proceeding from Nil.Pfahl, (6 documents WorldPerfect5.Windows); Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - Discussion Notes - Karen Escolas, undated; wiessner_c_042; Karen Escolas, Word 6.0: Discussion Notes, April 17th; Discussion Notes, April 16th; Belenky Notes, April 17th; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - Focus Groups and General Sessions, undated; wiessner_c_032; Focus Group; Discourse; Reflection; etc.; Focus Group - Workplace Orgn.; General Sessions - Mezirow, Kegan, Brochfield, Cranton; By Peter Hess, (done); Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - GHI Story, undated; wiessner_c_040; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - International Conference on Transformative Learning, 3rd, 2000
    - TLC, 2000; wiessner_c_028; TLC, (2000), (From Ann M. - done): TLDay1.wpd; TLDay2.wpd, (includes Kegan); Mary Belenb.wpd; Larry Datoz.wpd (Includes day3, recommendation); Victoria Marsick.wpd; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
    - TLC 2000, wiessner_c_036; TLC 2000: TLC.paper.Janice.E.Clark. “Imagining Otherwise”. IBM -PC Windows 98; Microsoft Word 2000. Second and Final Submission; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
    - TLC 2000, wiessner_c_037; TLC 2000: Presentation Notes - Stephen Brookfield: “The Critical Reflection Dimension”, from Lunda J. Belknap, Ed. D.; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
    - TLC Email list 2000; UNC Job App; Supporting Documents, wiessner_c_035; TLC Email list 2000; UNC Job App; Supporting Doc., etc.; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - International Conference on Transformative Learning, undated
    - TLC, undated; wiessner_c_020; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
    - TLC, undated; wiessner_c_021; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
    - TLC, undated; wiessner_c_022; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
    - TLC, undated; wiessner_c_041; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
    - TL Conference: “Cosmic Heroes...”, Joanne Gozawa, undated; wiessner_c_045; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
    - TLC Proceedings, undated; wiessner_c_019; Misc. Disst. Purpose Grid: TLC Proceedings: Tara Amann; Ed O’Sullivan; Dororthy Ettling; Sue; Scoth; Hazi; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - JKL, undated; wiessner_c_023; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - Mezirow Chapter, undated; wiessner_c_033; Mezirow Chapter: H. Prop; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - [Mezirow] Files, undated; wiessner_c_024; Mez. Files: Brannon; Yarosz; Davis; Cohen; Muhihill; Valek; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - [Mezirow] Files, undated; wiessner_c_025; Mez. Files: Wallis; Gozawa (update); Lopez, (sent w/ Luddy, Latson, Lopez); Alnadeff; Tisdele, (update); Sawyer (1); Sawyer (2); Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - [Mezirow] Files, undated; wiessner_c_026; Mez. Files: Luddy, Lopez; Latson; Taylor, Sawyer, Dirkx; Smith Brown; Cranton, Roy, Linline; Cranton; Golia; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - [Mezirow] Files: Early doctoral files to use, review, undated; wiessner_c_027; Mez. Files: Early doctoral files to use/ review; TLC too?; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - [Mezirow] Files: ECCW Workshop, undated; wiessner_c_017; Mez. Files: ECCW Workshop: Jenson - Quad; Taylor - Women in City; Peddigrew; O’Neill; Coleman; Diaz; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - National Conference on Transformative Learning, 1st, 1998
    - Changing Adult Frames of Reference, Conference Proceedings of The First National Conference on Transformative Learning, 04/15/1998; 04/17/1998; wiessner_c_043; Conference Proceedings, The First National Conference on Transformative Learning, (April 15-17, 1998); Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
    - Insights from the First National Conference on Transformative Learning, undated; wiessner_c_039; Colleen Aalsburg Wiessner [sic] and Cheryl A. Smith, 1. Chapter; 2. Colleen Bio; 3. Cheryl Bio, (Word 97); Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - Sharon Lamm’s Research Notes, undated; wiessner_c_030; Sharon Lamm’s Research Notes - world perfect 6.1; Good, Kegan back up, (done); Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - Teams; Vattimo; L. O., undated; wiessner_c_034; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - TL Book Chapter, undated; wiessner_c_038; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
  - Transformative Learning as Meaning Becoming Clarified, J. Mezirow; Microsoft Word, undated; wiessner_c_016; Floppy disk: 3 1/2 inch (Box 4)
- Conferences, See Computer media for more material relating to the International Conference on Transformative Learning.
  - International Conference on Transformative Learning, 3rd, 2000; 5 folders; includes conference proceedings (Box 2)
    See also Computer media: International Conference on Transformative Learning, 3rd, 2000.
  - International Conference on Transformative Learning, 4th, 2001; 3 folders; includes papers presented at conference (Box 2)
  - International Conference on Transformative Learning, 5th, 2003; conference proceedings (Box 2)
  - International Conference on Transformative Learning, 6th, 2005 (Box 2)
  - International Conference on Transformative Learning, 8th, 2009 (Box 2)
  - National Conference on Transformative Learning, 1st, 1998; See also Computer media: National Conference on Transformative Learning, 1st, 1998. (Box 2)
  - National Conference on Transformative Learning, 2nd, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Standing Conference on University Teaching and Research in the Education of Adults, 34th, 2004 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified conferences, expenses, 2001-2002 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified conference, participant feedback, 2006 (Box 2)
- Professional work
  - Focus groups, undated; topics, schedules, and instructions for researchers (Box 3)
  - NCSU New Learning Project, undated; 2 folders; participant feedback (Box 3)
  - Notes, undated; 3 folders; thoughts on education theory, for unidentified talk or paper (Box 3)
- Writings
  - Choreographing theory development, undated (Box 3)
  - Reflections on a happening, undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Where have we been? Where are we going?, undated (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  - Abstracts, 2000-2006; includes material by Jack Mezirow (Box 3)
  - Photographs, undated; 4 folders; some depicting unidentified conference (Box 3)
  - Printed material, 2000-2007 (Box 3)